- Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
We're going to explain
this mysterious photo
as we go through the class
and let's go to the Tibetan.
The name of this class by
the way, of this session,
is called, We Never Know Who People Are.
And here's the Tibetan of the Lam Rim.
'DI BSGOM PA NA
If you keep up this meditation
that I asked you to treasure
and not lose the tradition
that I worked so hard to get,
DANG POR TSE 'DI' AA
MAS SKYE BA SNGA MA'I MA
MANG DU BYAS PAR BSGOM
start with your mom in this life
and think about how many past lives
she was your mom, over and over.
Then, now we expand and we have a picture
of an expanding circle of water.
Think about: now expand the vision,
like the ripples in a pond
when you drop a stone in the middle.
Expand it to your dad.
Expand it to your father in this life.
My dad in this life has been
my mom in countless lives.
So expand it to your father.
Start with your mom in this life,
Imagine that she's been
your mom countless times.
Then when you're ready,
expand it to your father.
PHA LA BSGOM
Expand the meditation to your father.
DE NAS GNYEN GZHAN DANG
Then expand it to other relatives:
uncles, aunts, grandparents, whatever.
Then, DE NAS BAR MA
Then go to people that you don't know.
People you've never met.
I don't know.
I have some neighbors in my neighborhood
that I have never talked to them.
I like them, I mean,
we smiled at each other
but they're not relatives.
They're just kind of
neutral people in my life.
DE DAG LA MNYONG BA LEGS PAR THON
MNYONG BA THON
means you got good at it.
It means experience has flowed out.
It's an idiom in Tibetan
that means once you get good
at working on your mom and your dad
and then other relatives
and people you don't know much about,
then you're ready for DGRA, Tim?
DGRA BCOM PA
- [Student] For?
- Enemy.
- [Student] Enemy.
- Yeah.
Then you're ready for your enemies.
It's called Ari in Sanskrit, Ari Hat,
means enemy destroyer.
So DGRA LA DMIGS NAS
Focus on your enemies.
People you don't like and
MA BYAS PAR BSAMS
think about, this MA is not negative.
It means they served as your mom
MA BYAS PA
They did your mom.
Think about it.
BSAMS RJES
Until, BSAMS RJES means after that
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD LA DMIGS TE SBYONG
till you get to the point
where you can do it
towards all living beings.
He doesn't mention animals and bugs
but that's what SEMS CAN can mean
in colloquial Tibetan.
That's expanded to non-humans.
All right, so this idea of
expanding the meditation.
'O NA
Now very interesting and famous objection.
He's trying to sell us a car.
Pabongka Rinpoche is
trying to sell us a car
called MAR SHES,
realize that everyone is your mom.
Then in every sales pitch
there's objections, right?
The customer makes objections.
This car, there's not a lot of
electricity charging stations
in the middle of Arizona.
Then the salesman has to
come back and say, "No,
but there's so many being put in!"
So here's the objection from
the customer, which is us:
MA YIN MA NGO SHES DGOS
If someone were my mom, I would know.
I would know, come on.
If someone had spent 20,
30, 40 years feeding me,
raising me, teaching me everything.
Look, I'm not stupid.
I would recognize her.
I would know.
DGOS
DE MI SHES PAS MA MIN NO SNYAM NA
And since I don't
recognize these strangers
have been my mom, they
have not been my mom.
If they had been my mom,
I would have this feeling towards them.
I would feel the connection.
But I don't feel the connection.
So I don't think they've been my mom.
Then here comes Pabongka
Rinpoche salesman answer:
SANGS RGYAS KYIS KYANG,
MA MA BYAS PA'I SEMS CAN
GCIG KYANG MA GZIGS
Even a Buddha is incapable
of perceiving with their own eyes
that anyone has not been their mother.
MA MA BYAS
Mother not done mother.
Even a Buddha does not have the capacity
to recognize that anyone
has not been their mother.
RANG RES NGO MA SHES PA MA GTOGS
MA DNGOS GNAS YIN TE
Okay, I agree,
You don't feel like they were your mom.
You don't feel a connection
to them, I understand.
But the Buddha does.
The person who sees all
things, sees that connection.
So I understand you don't
feel a connection like that.
I understand, but you're
just stupid and wrong.
Because Buddha who sees all things says,
"They have been."
So don't think that you're going to,
if you don't have an emotional
connection to somebody
they have never been your mother
in the past life. Don't think like that.
Looks can be deceiving.
There are people who are,
people are not what they seem
and people are not what they feel.
And I like to give this
example of this next photo.
So, here you see me with Venerable Jigme
and my wife Veronica.
We are giving a down payment
for this little tiny cafe
we are buying from this couple.
This couple is in their 70's.
The lady whose name
is, nickname is Cricket
because she's about this tall.
When they were on their
honeymoon a 100 years ago,
the guy who ran the
bed and breakfast said,
told the husband, the new husband,
"Hey, don't loose that cricket.
Don't let that cricket
fall out of your bed,
you're going to lose her."
After that, they called the
cafe Crickets, after the wife.
So she ran the cooking.
Can you keep it up?
She ran the kitchen,
and then he would, on the weekends,
he would show up and
pour coffee for people.
He would just say... He'd
come up, he's very shy
and he'd say, "Would you
like some more coffee?"
And I was talking to people,
I used to hang out there,
"Maybe he's retarded a little bit? Or..."
It's just kind of, they
just gave him the coffee
and said, "Ask people, do
they need more coffee?"
Then later I found out
he's one of the leading
astronomers in the world.
He's been running the
observatory, Lowell Observatory
where they discovered Pluto.
He discovered the
atmosphere of Pluto himself,
and he's tracking thousands of asteroids
to make sure they don't
crash into this planet.
And he invented the
systems for tracking them.
Then I'm like suddenly,
I'm like, "He's not this dull
guy who's pouring coffee,
he's a world famous astronomer!"
He's one of the greatest
astronomers alive today.
What's the lesson here?
Just because you don't
feel like he's a genius
doesn't mean he's not a genius.
Just because you don't feel
like someone is your mom,
maybe your feelings are wrong.
Maybe your impression of this guy is wrong
and maybe he's not what you think he is.
And the older you get in this life,
Gyelse can tell you, right?
The more you've realized
that you meet people
and you're completely wrong about them.
TSE 'DI'I MA YANG PHYIS
KHYI LTA BUR SKYES NAS
YOD KYANG RANG GIS MI SHES
Look, even the mother you had
in this life, we don't know
what she will be in her next life.
She could be a dog. We don't know.
She could be your pet dog.
Your pet dog could be your mother
who died earlier in your
life. We don't know.
LTA BUR SKYES NAS YOD
KYANG RANG GIS MI SHES
Maybe you don't understand,
maybe you just don't know.
TSE 'DI'I MA DNGOS GNAS PA YANG
NGO MI SHES PA YOD PA
TSE 'DI'I MA
And you have to read,
Tim you have to read DNGOS GNAS PA
DNGOS GNAS PA goes together.
DNGOS GNAS PA
And DNGOS GNAS PA means the real one,
the genuine one.
It's an idiom.
DNGOS GNAS PA means the real one
So even there's cases where people
get separated from their mother
and they don't even recognize
them when they meet them.
Like this person, I
recently heard about a lady
who gave up her daughter for adoption
or her son for adoption,
when her son was born,
and later they met each other
and they used to hang out together
and they didn't know
they were mother and son.
They just didn't know.
Then suddenly they figured it out,
they were, "Oh my God...", so it happens.
If your mom died in this life,
she could be born as a dog, as your dog.
And you wouldn't know, and you
wouldn't have that feeling.
There is even people who
get separated from their mom
in this life who later meet their mom,
and don't recognize her.
So don't think you have to recognize her.
DGE SLONG MA AUTPA LA'I
MDOG GI LO RGYUS DANG
Think about the story of
the nun called Utpala Varna,
which means the color of the Blue Lotus.
The lovely Blue Lotus.
And there's a nun by this name.
Think about this story of
PHA SHA ZA ZHING MA LA 'TSOG
That's a piece of a poem.
And it's part of a longer
poem that is a sutra.
The part here says,
"This guy is eating his father's flesh
and beating his mom on the head,
smacking his mom on the head."
'TSOG means, different spelling,
it means smacking.
You guys know the story, right?
So a family lived next to a pond.
The father used to catch
fishes there all the time.
He used to eat the fish.
Later... and the mom was
very attached to the house.
Then they both died.
They had kids and they died.
They had a son and they died.
Then the father was reborn
as a fish in the pond, behind the house.
We had the story in the Lam Rim.
We gave you the whole story.
The mom died and was born as a dog
who was owned by the son,
and the dog was attached to the house
and used to growl at anybody
who would come in the house,
because in the past life,
the dog had been the mom who
was attached to the house.
Then the guy gets married.
He has the dog.
He's still fishing out back,
the lake behind the house,
the pond behind the house.
He is catching his father sometimes
and eating him at dinner.
Then the father dies again.
Then the father is born in the pond again.
Then the son catches another fish,
and that's a father again.
Then he eats that fish.
Now on top of all that,
there is a guy who is
attracted to his wife
and has an affair with his wife,
and he goes and kills the guy.
Because the guy was attracted
to his wife's sexual organs,
he's born in the wife's
womb and he's their son.
So, basically this guy is
eating his, when he's at dinner
the dog's trying to get
the fish off the plate
and he's beating the dog,
smacking the dog on the head,
which is his mom. And
he's eating his father.
And he's hugging the guy who
had adultery with his wife,
on his lap, who is his son.
Then is it Maudgalyayana goes
and asks for some leftovers
for his begging bowl.
And the guy says, get
the hell out of here.
Then another monk comes over and says,
"You have no idea who is Maudgalyayana,
he can travel to 1,000 planets for dinner.
He doesn't need your food.
He's trying to help you."
By the way, and then
he tells him the story
of what's going on in his house.
So we don't always recognize
who the people around us
have been in the past.
There's all kinds of people in our lives
who might be people we knew before.
I've met people I thought were
my mom, and stuff like that.
We don't know. We don't really know.
Alright, now the story
about the nun named Utpala
is fascinating for me
because we have a nun named
Utpala, who we love very much.
And as I said, I don't know the story.
I went and found the story
for you guys, which is my job
And I enjoy that job.
AI went and found the story
of the Blue Lotus, Utpala,
and here's a blue lotus picture for you,
just to get in the mood.
She's called Utpala Varna.
I found the story in a sutra called
MDO MDZANGS BLUN
Say MDO MDZANGS BLUN
I love the name of the sutra
because it means the Sutra
of the Wise and Foolish.
The Sutra called Wise People and Fools,
which is such a beautiful name.
I mean, it would make a
good name for any book.
So I read the story, it's extremely old.
As apparently the sutra is very, very old
and it was difficult to read.
A couple of times I stopped
and I said, "It's too much,
I don't have time to try
to figure out the story."
But I worked it through
and I'd like to teach it to you guys.
It's worth it, it's worth it.
So here we go.
By the way, her story
was summarized briefly
in this Lam Rim before, but
I'm giving you the whole story.
So here we go.
'CI' PHYIR
You got the 'CI' PHYIR?
'CI' PHYIR DE DAG
I'm sorry, let's start below that.
DE NAS
And then four paragraphs below.
DE NAS DGE SLONG
Mr. Tim, skip four lines down,
Skip 4 paragraphs down.
Yeah, DE NAS, 347
Good, okay.
DE NAS DGE SLONG MA DE DAG
So this story begins with
a bunch of Buddhist nuns
who approach a senior nun.
DGE SLONG MA DE DAG
DGE SLONG MA AUTPA LA'I MDOG
GANG NA 'DUG PAR SONG NAS
These other nuns went
to where the Blue Lotus,
the nun named Blue lotus was sitting.
SONG NAS DER PHYIN PA DANG
AUTPA LA'I MDOG LA PHYAG 'TSAL
They made prostration to Blue Lotus
and CHOS BZHIN DU SNYUN GSOL NAS
'DI SKAD CES SMRAS SO
Then they paid respect to her properly
CHOS BZHIN DU
And they said, "We have
something to ask you."
Next paragraph.
BDAG CAG KHYIM NA MCHIS PA NA
KHYIM GYI LAS KYIS BSLUS
We tried the home life
and they cheated us,
BSLUS means deceived us.
We tried the wife thing and
it just didn't work out.
BSLUS NAS, DA RAB TU BYUNG
So we became ordained.
YANG 'DOD PA'I DBANG DU GYUR NAS
But still we have
attractions to the home life,
to sex, things like that, good clothes.
We still are NYON MONGS
but, by those ideas,
by those thoughts.
So here's an ancient
verb, which is klesha-ed.
We are still disturbed.
Remember the definition of
a mental affliction, right?
We are still disturbed
by thoughts of desire
for house, husband, clothes.
THAR PAR MI NUS
We could not get over that.
We could not moksha from that.
BDAG CAG LA THUGS BRTZE BA'I SLAD DU
If you love us,
THUGS BRTZE BA, honorific,
if you love us.
DAM PA'I CHOS BSTAN DU GSOL
please teach us the holy Dharma
to help us fix this
condition of attachment
to our old home life.
AUTPA LAS SMRAS PA
Then what do you want to
call it? Indigo Lotus?
That's nice. Indigo answered them.
KHYOD CI DANG CI 'DOD PA
'DAS PA'AM MA 'ONGS PA'AM,
DA LTAR GYI DNGOS PO
GANG YANG RUNG BA DRIS SHIG
GNAS BSTAN PAR BYA'O
Do you want me to talk
to you about situations
that are in the past,
or situations that happened in
will happen in the future,
or something that's going on nowadays?
What's the context?
Do you want a story from old days?
Do you want a story from the future?
By the way, at this point she was an arhat
and there's a beautiful story
of her becoming an arhat.
So she's an arhat and she's like,
"You want me to tell the future?
You want me to go over past?
Which one do you want?"
NGAS BSTAN PAR BYA'O
I agree to teach you, but tell me what
timeframe you guys are talking about?
DGE SLONG MA RNAMS KYIS 'DAS PA DANG
MA 'ONGS PA RE ZHIG ZHOG
RE ZHIG ZHOG means let's forget the past
and future for today.
Just give us something going on now.
Give us something that's
going on now that can help us
get over our attachment
to the husbands and homes
we used to have.
BSTAN TE BDAG CAG GI
THE TSOM DGROL DU GSOL
And we ask you to liberate our doubts.
Free us from our doubts.
AUTPA LAS SMRAS PA
She answered,
'DOD CHAGS NI, ME DANG 'DRA STE
"Attachment to the worldly,
attachment to the home life
is like a huge fire, huge wildfire."
RI LUNG TSIG PAR BYED DO
It can burn the mountains
and the valleys both.
RTZA 'KHRI DANG 'DRA STE
It's also like a family line
in the sense that it's exponential.
One person gives birth to a baby.
That person has two babies.
Those babies have four babies,
and desire tends to multiply upon itself.
Here's the word for SKYE MCHED, Tim,
in āyatana, in the Abhidharma.
We call it door of sense,
but it really means
exponential door of sense.
One perception of an object
can lead to a 1,000 thoughts.
'DOD CHAGS KYI DBANG GIS GCIG LA GCIG 'TSE
Due to their attachment to things
people hurt each other.
GNOD PAR BYED - They do
damage to each other.
DE LA YUN RING NA NGAN
SONG GSUM DU LHUNG STE
If that goes on for any length of time
then we fall into the three lower realms.
THAR PA'I DUS MED DO
It's almost impossible to free ourselves
once we are in the lower realms.
KHYIM NA GNAS PA NI
SDUG PA LA CHAGS TE 'DOD PA DANG
BYE BRAL BA DANG
The definition of having
a home and a husband
and all these things
is almost like you are trying to
practice attachment
and the fear of disattachment,
the fear of losing things.
By living the home life
you are a study in attachment
and the fears of losing what you have.
SKYE BA DANG, RGA BA DANG,
NA BA DANG, 'CHI BA DANG
RGYAL PO'I KHRIMS KYIS
GTZE BA'I SDUG BSNGAL
RGYUN MI CHAD PAR MYONG STE
It's a constant flow of
rebirth, aging, illness, death,
and the injustices of
the government, she says.
I don't know why she threw that in there.
That's probably close
to tax day or something.
Injustices in the government.
I don't know.
I don't know there's probably
another sutra about that.
TSE 'PHOS NAS PHYIR YANG SOS PA TZAM DU
After you die, that
attachment to your house,
to your home has other effects on you.
The effects continue after you die.
YANG SOS PA TZAM DU LUS
He says, even if you just fall to the
hell called Revive.
So it's either a reference
to the hell called Revive
or that those attachments
will revive themselves.
They will come back to you. Either way,
they will continue. The
repercussions of desire
in this life continuing
into future life, GDUNGS TE
SEMS GDUNGS
They torture your mind
KHYIM GYIS GLAGS SHING BCINGS PA NI
BTZON RABS KYANG DAM MO
To put it briefly,
living in the home life for
a woman is like a prison.
That's her final word on this.
I want to stop there today.
Tim and me agreed that would be nice
to give you guys a break
sometimes, a shorter class.
So we're going to stop that class there,
and we'll be going on
and continuing with the
story of Blue Lotus,
this nun whose name is Blue Lotus.
It's a story that you will never forget
and that's the idea of putting
a story in the Lam Rim.
See you in the next class.